Register of the Wayne Holder papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Wayne Holder papers
1920-2007
2006C39
Holder, Wayne, 1949-
7 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (4.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Acquired in 2006, the papers consist primarily of correspondence, writings, and photographs relating to the history and literature of Estonia. Of particular importance are the numerous photographs and writings in the papers that pertain to the struggle for renewed independence for Estonia in the years leading up to the break up of the Soviet Union in 1991.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audio recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1949 Born, Colorado
1982-1983 With Toomas Ilves, runs The Literary Storefront, a cultural center in Vancouver, British Columbi
1984 Travels to Estonia, then part of the Soviet Union. Meets with Estonian writers
1988 Guest editor of Cake, a literary journal. Issue has special section devoted to modern Estonian writing
1989-1990 Travels twice to Estonia, documents independence movement
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2006, the Wayne Holder papers in the Hoover Institution Archives consist primarily of correspondence, writings, and photographs relating to the history and literature of Estonia. Of particular importance are the numerous photographs and writings in the papers that pertain to the struggle for renewed independence for Estonia in the years leading up to the break up of the Soviet Union in 1991.
Holder's interest in Estonia dates from the early 1980s, when he lived in Vancouver, B.C. and was close friends with Toomas Ilves, an Estonian-American also living in Vancouver. Holder and Ilves collaborated on the translation of works by a number of Estonian poets, including Marie Under. They were also for a time active in running the Literary Storefront, a cultural center in Vancouver that hosted public readings by many authors.
Holder first visited Estonia in 1984, when it was still part of the Soviet Union, and he met with a number of Estonian writers. He again visited Estonia in 1989 and 1990, when the independence movement there was gathering momentum, and both took and collected numerous photographs documenting this phenomenon. He also met with various cultural figures, from established writers to young members of the Estonian punk scene.
The Correspondence series in the papers contains a significant number of letters from Toomas Ilves, who later repatriated to Estonia and became that country's president, as well as from the Estonian writer, Juhan Habicht. The Speeches and Writings series is comprised mainly of poems that reflect Holder's experiences in Estonia. The Writings by others series consists largely of translations of works by Estonian writers. The Photographs and Oversize materials series contain many photographs that document the rise of the independence movement in Estonia during 1989-1990. There are also a large number of photographs (in the Oversize materials series) that originated in the photo services of the Union of Soviet Societies of Friendship and Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries. These depict scenes of economic and political life in the Soviet Union, largely in the late 1970s.
The papers also contain a quantity of research materials from Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, and which consist of wire service reports and articles from serial issues that relate to Estonia, Eastern Europe, and the Soviet Union. These materials were sent to Holder by Toomas Ilves in the mid-1980s, when Ilves was head of the Estonian desk of Radio Free Europe in Munich.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 11 series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Notes and writing fragments, Writings by others, Research materials, Subject file, Printed matter, Photographs, Sound recording, and Oversize materials
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Estonian literature.; Estonia Civilization.; Estonia Social conditions.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1983-2007; 1 (Box 1:)
  Contains article, correspondence, and photocopies, relating to literary activities and travels of Holder, arranged by physical form.
  - Correspondence, maps of Tartu and Tallinn, and travel brochure, 1983-1984 (Folder 1: 1)
  - History of The Literary Storefront, article, 2007 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Passport pages and visa issued for the Soviet Union, photocopies, and letter of invitation from the Estonian Writers Union, 1990 (Folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1983-2004; 1 (Box 1: 3)
  Contains letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1985-1989 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Bullock, Merry, 1984-1990 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Ellison, John, 1986 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Habicht, Juhan, 1984-1991 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Ilves, Toomas (Tom), 1983-1986 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Keenan, Johanna, 2004 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kitching, Juta, 1986 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Kross (?), Jaan, 1985 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Kurman, George, 1984-1990 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Murray, John, 1984 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Olljum, Alar, 1985-1989 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Talts, Helga, 1984-1985 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Tamm, Riina, 1986 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Venclova, Tomas, 1985-1990 (Folder 1: 17)
- Speeches and writings, 1983-1991; 1-2 (Box 1-2: 17)
  Consists primarily of poems and other writings about Estonia.
  - "An Age of Exile," poem, 1983 (Folder 1: 18)
  - "The Astronomer's Wife," poem, 1983 (Folder 1: 19)
  - "Born in Exile," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 20)
  - "Coming to Know," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Dreaming on Our Feet," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Estonia essay, 1984 (Folder 1: 24)
  - George Orwell article, 1984 (Folder 1: 25)
  - "Last Words to...," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 26)
  - "More Famous Last Words," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 27)
  - "Night Watchmen," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 28)
  - "On the Field of Mars," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 29)
  - "Revolt of the Schoolchildren," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 30)
  - "Sunbathing," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 31)
  - "Table Talk in Tallinn," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 32)
  - "To the Flowers of Tallinn," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 33)
  - "Too Cold," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Untitled poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Untitled poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 36)
  - "Visit to a Small Country," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 37)
  - "Watching the Seagulls," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 38)
  - "The Word Was There Before Me," poem, 1984 (Folder 1: 39)
  - "In Russian, To Be Silent Is an Active Verb," poem, 1985 (Folder 1: 40)
  - "The Fifteenth Official Language," Cake, vol. 2., no. 1, 1988 (Folder 2:)
    Issue contains a special section on Estonian literature edited by Holder
    - Correspondence and typescript drafts, 1988 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Printed copy, 1988 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Autobiographical novel (incomplete), 1991 (Folder 2: 3-8)
  - To Be Remembered in the Kingdom of the Rats, 1991 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Young Estonia 1991 (Folder 2: 10)
- Notes and writing fragments, 1984-1990; 2-3 (Box 2-3: 10)
  Consists of incomplete drafts of poems and notes, largely relating to Estonia.
  - Notebooks, 1984-1990 (Folder 2:)
    - 1984 (Folder 2: 11-12)
    - 1990 (Folder 3: 1-2)
  - Notes and fragments, 1984-1990 (Folder 3: 3-4)
- Writings by others, 1936-1990; 3-4 (Box 3-4: 3-4)
  Contains original texts and translations of poems, largely by Estonian writers.
  - Unidentified, 1984-1990 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Alver, Betti, 1936-1939 (Folder 3: 6)
    English translations by George Kurman.
  - Habicht, Juhan, 1987 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Hurley, Maureen, 1990 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Ilves, Toomas, 1984 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Kareva, Doris, 1983-1985 (Folder 3: 10)
    English translations by Toomas Ilves.
  - Luik, Viivi, 1968 (Folder 3: 11)
    English translations by Riina Tamm.
  - Rävää, Annus (pseudonym of Helmut Tarand), 1984 (Folder 3: 12)
    In Estonian, with English translations by Wayne Holder and Toomas Ilves.
  - Sermat, Vello, 1989 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Under, Marie, 1958-1963 (Folder 3: 14-16)
  - Under, Marie, 1958-1963 (Folder 4: 1-2)
    (Contd.)
  - Vahing, Vaino, 1990 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Venclova, Tomas, 1988 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Zoltán, Sumonyi, 1985 (Folder 4: 5)
- Research materials, 1984-1992; 4-5 (Box 4-5: 5)
  Consists of wire service reports and articles, largely relating to Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Eastern Europe, and the Soviet Union.
  - Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, 1984-1986 (Folder 4:)
    - Background reports, 1984-1985 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Research bulletins, 1984-1985 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Wire service reports and articles from serial issues, 1984-1986 (Folder 4:)
      - 1984 (Folder 4: 8-10)
      - 1985 (Folder 4: 11)
      - 1985 (Folder 5: 1-4)
      - 1986 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Baltic Republics Discussion List, 1991-1992 (Folder 5:)
    - 1991 (Folder 5: 6-9)
    - 1992 (Folder 5: 10-11)
- Subject File, 1958-1991; 6 (Box 6:)
  Contains clippings and articles, largely relating to Estonia, Estonian literature, and the Soviet Union.
  - Armenia, 1978-1985 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Baltic States, 1988-1991 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Environment--Soviet Union, 1992 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Estonia, 1980-1991 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Gorbachev, Mikhail, 1988 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Jääger, Merle, 1988-1989 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Kaplinski, Jaan, 1978-1988 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Soviet Union--History, 1988-1990 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Under, Marie, 1958-1983 (Folder 6: 9)
- Printed matter, 1985-1990; 6-7 (Box 6-7: 9)
  Consists of serial issues and monographs, largely relating to Estonia, Estonian-Americans, and Estonian culture.
  - Serial issues, 1985-1990 (Folder 6:)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985-1990 (Folder 6: 10)
    - Cake, vol. 2, no. 1, 1988 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Eesti Elu, 1990 March (Folder 6: 2)
    - Esto America, 1984 January-September/October (Folder 6: 13)
    - Keel ja Kirjandus, no. 6, 1988 (Folder 6: 14)
    - Looming, no. 2, 1990 (Folder 6: 15)
    - Vikerkaar, no. 3, 1989 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Monographs, 1985-1989 (Folder 7:)
    - Siniland, Sirje, Viro Ja Venäjä, 1985 (Folder 7: 1)
    - E Stuudio, 1989 (Folder 7: 2)
- Photographs, 1920-1990; 7 (Box 7: 2)
  Consists of negatives, contact sheets, and prints, largely relating to scenes and personalities in Estonia.
  - Negatives, 1990 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Contact sheets, 1990 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Estonia, 1989-1990 (Folder 7:)
    - Unidentified, 1989-1990 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Folk dancers, 1990 (Folder 7: 6)
    - Independence movement, 1989-1990 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Tallinn and Rocca-al-Mare, 1990 (Folder 7: 8-11)
  - Estonian House and Estonian legation (former site), London, England, 1990 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Finland, 1990 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Holder, Wayne, 1990 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Ilves, Toomas, 1990 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Kelam, Tunne, 1990 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Leningrad, 1990 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Under, Marie, 1920 (Folder 7: 18)
- Sound recordings, 1973-1983; 7 (Box 7: 19)
  Consists of one audio cassette of readings of Estonian poetry.
- Oversize materials, 1978-1990; 8-10 (Box 8-10: 18)
  Contains a poster, miscellaneous serial issues, a scrapbook of photographs taken in Estonia and compiled by Holder, and large-size photographs depicting economic and political life in the Soviet Union.
  - Holder, Wayne, scrapbook with numerous photographs depicting scenes and personalities in Estonia, 1987-1990 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Kaplinski, Jaan, poster announcing publication of his book, The Same Sea in Us All, 1985 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Miscellaneous serial issues, 1985-1990 (Folder 8: 3)
  - "The USSR--A Society of True Democracy," exhibit of large-size photographs produced by the Union of Soviet Societies of Friendship and Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries, Moscow, 1978 (Folder 9: 1-4)
  - "Socialist Economic Integration in Action," exhibit of large-size photographs produced by the Union of Soviet Societies of Friendship and Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries, Moscow, 1978 (Folder 10: 1)
  - "Vladimir and Suzdal Historico-Architectural Preserve," exhibit of large-size photographs produced by the Union of Soviet Societies of Friendship and Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries, Moscow, 1979 (Folder 10: 2)